Guide to the E. Roy Weintraub Papers, 1930-2019 and undated RL.11763
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
E. Roy Weintraub papers
1930-2019 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Weintraub, E. Roy
RL.11763
15.5 Linear Feet 12 boxes
1.1 Gigabytes
E. Roy Weintraub (b.1943) is Professor Emeritus of Economics at Duke University. This collection consists of his correspondence, research, and writings.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into series: Correspondence, Conferences and Organizations, Writings, and Research and Notes. Series contain name and topic folders sorted alphabetically.
Biographical / Historical
E. Roy Weintraub (b.1943) is Professor Emeritus of Economics at Duke University and a Fellow at the Center for the History of Political Economy. Weintraub joined Duke in 1970. His work in the history of economics, particularly the mathematization of economics and history of general equilibrium theory, has been influential in shaping the field and bringing historical methods to the foreground of the history of economics. Weintraub also played key roles in building and developing the Economists' Paper Archive and the Center for the History of Political Economy at Duke. He served as Director of Graduate Studies in the Department of Economics from 1972 to 1983, Department Chair from 1983 to 1987, Acting Director of the Institute of Statistics and Decision Sciences in 1987, Director of the Center for Social and Historical Studies of Science from 1995 to 1999, and chaired Duke's Academic Council. From 1993 to 1995, he served as Acting Dean of the Faculty of Arts and Sciences, and in 1992 received the Howard Johnson Foundation Distinguished Undergraduate Teaching Award. He has also been a fellow at the National Humanities Center. Weintraub holds an A.B. in mathematics from Swarthmore College and a Ph.D. in applied mathematics from the University of Pennsylvania (completed under the supervision of Lawrence Klein). He is the son of economist Sidney Weintraub.
Access Restrictions
The collection's correspondence is restricted for ten years following the date of its creation. Contact Research Services to request permission to view recent correspondence.
Provenance
The E. Roy Weintraub Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift beginning in 1984, with the vast majority of the collection arriving in 2019.
Related Materials
E. Roy Weintraub is the son of economist Sidney Weitraub. The Sidney Weintraub papers are also included in the Rubenstein Library collections.
Collection Overview
The E. Roy Weintraub Papers document his career as a historian of economics and mathematics, and professor at Duke University. The collection provides an overview of his professional activities, particularly his research and writings on the history of economics, role in the community of history of economics scholars, and as a faculty member and administrator at Duke.
The collection also documents his communications with prominent economists as research subjects such as Kenneth Arrow, Gerard Debreu, and Lionel McKenzie. Included in Weintraub's communications are exchanges with prominent figures in the history of economics and related communities of scholars such as Roger Backhouse, Bradley Bateman, Anthony Brewer, Arjo Klamer, Mary Morgan, Deirdre McCloskey, and Philip Mirowski.
Along with his own scholarship and writings, the collection documents Weintraub's roles at in the History of Economics Society, at Duke University, and as an editor of History of Political Economy.
Conditions Governing Access
Some files from Weintraub's service as Acting Dean are restricted for 25 years from date of creation. Files related to the Duke Board of Trustees are restricted for 50 years from date of creation. Files related to faculty recruitment and personnel reviews are restricted for 75 years from date of creation.
Conditions Governing Access
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection contains electronic records that must be requested through the collection guide and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services to request the production of use copies.
Economics; Economics -- Philosophy; Economics -- Sociological aspects; Neoclassical school of economics -- History; Economics -- History; Economics -- Methodology; Equilibrium (Economics); History of Economic Thought; Economics -- Mathematical models; Game theory; Mathematics -- History; Klein, Lawrence R. (Lawrence Robert), 1920-2013; Weintraub, Sidney, 1914-1983; Arrow, Kenneth J. (Kenneth Joseph), 1921-2017; Debreu, Gerard; McKenzie, Lionel W.; Samuelson, Paul A. (Paul Anthony), 1915-2009; Solow, Robert M.; Davidson, Paul, 1930-; Goodwin, Craufurd D. W.; McCloskey, Deirdre N.; Patinkin, Don; History of Economics Society; History of political economy; Duke University. Department of Economics; Bronfenbrenner, Martin, 1914-1997; Clower, Robert W.; Journal of Economic Literature; American Economic Association
- Correspondence, 1943-2017 and undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series documents Weintraub's professional and personal communications. Notable correspondents include Kenneth Arrow, Gerard Debreu, Deirdre McCloskey, Lionel McKenzie, Phil Mirowski, Don Patinkin, Paul Samuelson, and Robert Solow, among others. Also of note is Weintraub's correspondence with his father Sidney Weintraub and other family members. Files are arranged alphabetically. Given the original arrangement of materials, some correspondence was kept in the Writings and Research series.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Correspondence files are restricted for 10 years following their date of creation. Contact Research Services to request access.
  - Alphabetical Correspondence, 1958-2008; undated; 1
    This subseries includes Weintraub's professional correspondence. Some personal correspondence with Sidney Weintraub is included since their communications bridged personal and professional purposes. Files were originally grouped by large spans of time but have been arranged into alphabetical name files.
    - A, 1993-2000 (Box 1)
    - Atkinson, Anthony, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - B, 1990-1998 (Box 1)
    - Backhouse, Roger, 1988-1992 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about exchanging research papers
    - Bateman, Bradley, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
      Includes letters discussing the role of interpretation in history of economics, methodology, and writings by Bateman and Weintraub
    - Bausor, Randall, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Boumans, Marcel, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Brewer, Anthony A., 1986-1996 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence discussing academic visits to Bristol, post-war economics, and rhetoric in economics
    - Bronfenbrenner, Martin, 1974-1992 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about the department at Duke and Weintraub's writings
    - Brown, Vivienne, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Burmeister, Edwin, 1990 (Box 1)
    - C, 1995-1997 (Box 1)
    - Caldwell, Bruce, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about seminars and economic methodology
    - Cambridge University Press, 1982-1994; 2 folders (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence related to Weintraub's role as consulting editor for textbooks
    - Charnov, Eric, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Clower, Robert, 1975 (Box 1)
      Includes a recommendation letter for Weintraub
    - Coats, A. W., 1993 (Box 1)
    - Cohen, Avi, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Cullenberg, Stephen, 1993 (Box 1)
    - D, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
    - Damon, William, 1990 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about the decline of history of economic thought at Vanderbilt
    - Davidson, Paul, 1975-1995 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about refereeing for the Journal of Post-Keynesian Economics, a recommendation letter for Weintraub, and other routine correspondence
    - Debreu, Gerard, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about Debreu visiting Duke, scheduling of interviews with Debreu, and the mathematization of economics
    - Dow, Sheila, 1991 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about exchange of papers
    - E, 1992; undated (Box 1)
    - F, 1992 (Box 1)
    - G, 1991-1997 (Box 1)
    - Galbraith, James, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Gates, Henry Louis, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about Gates's time at Duke
    - Goodstein, Judith, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Goodwin, Craufurd, 1991-1997 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about grants and proposed supplemental issues of History of Political Economy
    - H, 1987-2002 (Box 1)
    - Hands, D. Wade, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about History of Economics Society meetings and Weintraub's writings
    - Hausman, Daniel, 1990 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about general equilibrium theory and proofmaking
    - Heilbroner, Robert, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about contributing to a History of Political Economy symposium
    - Henderson, Willie, 1990 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about visiting University of Birmingham
    - Hollander, Samuel, 1993 (Box 1)
    - I, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Ikeo, Aiko, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about sending papers and meetings to discuss research
    - Israel, Giorgio, 1991-1994 (Box 1)
    - J, 2000; undated (Box 1)
    - Kim, Jinbang, 1990 (Box 1)
    - King, John E., 1992 (Box 1)
    - Klamer, Arjo, 1986-1993 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about Klamer's time at Wellesley and other routine matters
    - Kregel, Jan, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about visit to University of Bologna
    - L, 1991-1995 (Box 1)
    - Leonard, Robert, 1993 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about history of game theory and John von Neumann
    - Lilly, Greg, 1993 (Box 1)
    - M, 1989-2007 (Box 1)
    - Maki, Uskali, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Mandler, Michael, 1994 (Box 1)
    - McCloskey, Deirdre, 1985-1995 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about mathematics and statistics in economics, rhetoric, economic history, and McCloskey's personal life
    - McElroy, Marjorie, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Medema, Steven, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Milberg, William, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Mirowski, Philip, 1992-1997 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about exchanging papers, the Economists' Papers Archive, Alain Lewis, and other routine business
    - Morgan, Mary, 1991-2005 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about exchange of papers and other routine matters
    - Negishi, Takashi, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about International Economic Association conference
    - O'Gorman, Pascal, 2008 (Box 1)
    - P, 1991-1996 (Box 1)
    - Patinkin, Don, 1991 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about Patinkin visiting Duke
    - Penceval, John, 1991 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about reviews in the Journal of Economic Literature
    - Permissions, 1990 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about granting reprint permissions
    - Pickering, Andy, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - R, 1996-2000 (Box 1)
    - Referee Reports, 1986-2000 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence related to referee activity for academic journals
    - Rima, Ingrid, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Rosenberg, Alex, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Roth, Alvin, 1993 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about a paper on the history of experimental economics by Roth
    - S, 1991-1995 (Box 1)
    - Samuels, Warren J., 1993 (Box 1)
      Includes comments on Weintraub's paper on economic formalism
    - Samuelson, Paul, 2004-2008 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about the status of the history of economic thought in the economics discipline and Samuelson's 90th birthday
    - Schabas, Margaret, 1994 (Box 1)
      Includes routine correspondence
    - Screpanti, Ernesto, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Solow, Robert, 2004-2008 (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about the status of the history of economic thought in the economics discipline and other routine matters
    - Strassman, Diana, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - T, 1990 (Box 1)
    - V, 1992 (Box 1)
    - W, 1986-1995 (Box 1)
    - Weintraub, Sidney, 1958-1983; 2 folders (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence about joint work and of a personal nature
    - Williams, Hannah, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Wulwick, Nancy, 1991 (Box 1)
    - X, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Duke, 1970-2012; 2
    This subseries includes Weintraub's correspondence pertaining to Duke and in his role as a faculty member, administrator, and a member of the Duke community. Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
    In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records. Materials with restricted FERPA information in this subseries are labeled below.
    Files related to faculty recruitment and personnel reviews are restricted for 75 years from date of creation. Materials with restricted personnel information in this subseries are labeled below.
    Subseries contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room.
    - Board of Trustees, 1991-1992 (Box 11)
      Includes files from Weintraub's interactions with Board of Trustees during his service as Acting Dean.
      Board of Trustee files are restricted under university statute for 50 years from date of creation. Restriction ends in 2042.
    - Committee Work, 1991-2012 (Box 2)
      Includes routine correspondence related to Weintraub's service on various committees
    - Deanship, 1993-1995; 2 folders (Box 1)
      Includes routine correspondence and notes of congratulations related to Weintraub's service as Acting Dean of Arts and Sciences
    - Deanship, 1995-1996 (Box 11)
      Includes routine correspondence related to Weintraub's service as Acting Dean
      Administrative files from service as Acting Dean are restricted under university statute for 25 years from date of creation. Restriction ends in 2021.
    - Economics Department, 1970-2010; 2 folders (Box 2)
      Includes correspondence related to routine department business and Weintraub's activities in the department
    - Economists' Papers Archive, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Photos, 1993 (Box 2)
      Includes faculty profile photos
    - Miscellaneous Duke Correspondence, 2005-2007 (Box 2)
      Includes routine university correspondence
    - Promotion and Tenure Committee, 1978-1987 (Box 11)
      Includes correspondence with committee and files from service as committee member.
      Records from personnel reviews are restricted for 75 years from date of creation. Restriction ends in 2057.
    - Recruitment and Hiring, 1985-2000 (Box 11)
      Includes correspondence related to Economics Department and University hiring.
      Records for hiring and recruitment are restricted for 75 years from date of creation. Restriction ends in 2070.
    - Summer Session, 1991 (Box 2)
      Includes correspondence related to summer teaching
    - ASF Letters, 1980-2017; 225 files; approximately 5 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11763-SET-0003)
      Includes document files in WordPerfect, MS Word, PDF, Excel, rich text and plain text formats related to Weintraub's role as a faculty member.
      FERPA and personnel information restricted until 2092.
  - Personal, 1943-2004; undated; 3
    This subseries includes Weintraub's personal correspondence with family members and others; and some personal items.
    - Certificates and Diploma, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
    - College Admissions, 1960 (Box 2)
    - Family Letters, 1951-1999; undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
      Includes correspondence with family members and items once belonging to father, Sidney Weintraub, and brother, Neil.
    - Juvenalia, 1943-1968; undated (Box 2)
      Includes correspondence with family and photographs
    - Miscellaneous Personal Correspondence, 1991-2004 (Box 2)
    - Owen, Choices: Your Money and Your Life, 1981 (Box 2)
      Includes draft manuscript by Neil Owen
    - Scott's Hi-Q, 1960 (Box 2)
      Includes materials from a high school competition hosted by Scott Paper Company
    - Searches, 1985-1997; 2 folders (Box 2)
      Includes materials and correspondence related to job searches
    - Term Papers, 1960-1963; undated (Box 2)
      Includes papers and materials related to undergraduate coursework
- Conferences and Organizations, 1968-2014; 2
  This series documents Weintraub's speaking engagements at conferences and workshops and his role in professional organizations, including service on the boards of academic journals. Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Series contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact research services with questions.
  - American Economic Association (AEA), 1982-1986; 4 folders (Box 2)
    Includes files related to conference presentations and travel
  - American Economic Review Board, 1981-1984 (Box 2)
    Includes files from service on journal editorial board
  - Amsterdam - Klant Conference, 1985 (Box 2)
    Includes files related to conference in honor of Joop Klant
  - Barcelona and Lecce, 2014 (Box 2)
    Includes travel documentation
  - Boston Conference, 1986 (Box 2)
    Includes files from conference hosted by the Center for the Philosophy and History of Science at Boston University
  - Center for Social and Historical Studies of Science, 1990-1998 (Box 2)
    Includes files from Weintraub's involvement in center at Duke
  - Conference on Equilibrium Concepts in Economics, 1989 (Box 3)
    Includes files for conference at Universite Louis Pasteur
  - Cornell University, 1998 (Box 3)
    Includes invitation for seminar presentation
  - Duke Conference on Innovation in the Social Sciences, 1974 (Box 3)
    Includes conference program and related correspondence
  - Econometric Society, 1968 (Box 3)
    Includes files for presentation on Stability of Stochastic General Equilibrium Systems
  - ENS Cachan, 2009 (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence related to visit
  - ESF Exploratory Workshop, 2008 (Box 3)
    Includes files related to assessing research proposals
  - European Society for the History of Economic Thought (ESHET), 2006 (Box 3)
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1998 (Box 3)
    Includes grant proposal
  - History of Economic Thought Society of Australia, 1999 (Box 3)
    Includes conference program
  - History of Economics Society (HES), 1986-2011; 6 folders (Box 3)
    Includes files from conference presentations and travel
  - History of Game Theory Conference, 1989-1991; 2 folders (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence related to hosting conference for History of Political Economy journal at Duke
  - History of Science Society, 1987 (Box 3)
    Includes notes for presentation
  - International Congress of History of Science, 1997 (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence related to travel
  - Journal of Economic Literature Editorial Board, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence from service on editorial board
  - Keynes Conference, Wake Forest University, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
    Includes files related to accommodations
  - Keynes Mini-Symposium, 1993 (Box 3)
  - La Sapienza, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence related to visiting university in Rome
  - MacArthur Foundation, 1999 (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence related to service as nominator
  - Milan, 2005 (Box 3)
    Includes flyer for presentation at University of Milan
  - Montreal Talk, 1997 (Box 3)
    Includes flyer for presentation at University of Quebec - Montreal
  - Morgan and Rutherford Conference on US Economics, 1995-1997 (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence and other files for hosting conference for History of Political Economy journal at Duke
  - National Humanities Center, 1988-1993 (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence related to fellowship at the center
  - National Science Foundation (NSF), 1970-1998; 3 folders (Box 3)
    Includes files related to grant proposals
  - North Carolina Utilities Commission, 1979-1980; 4 folders (Box 3)
    Includes files related to expert testimony on economics of nuclear power in North Carolina
  - Notre Dame, 1991 (Box 4)
    Includes conference program and materials for presentation for Natural Images Conference
  - Paris, 2006 (Box 4)
    Includes travel documents
  - Rome, Athens, STOREP, 2007 (Box 4)
    Includes travel documents for multiple stops on trip to Europe as Visiting Scholar at La Sapienza
  - STS Talk, 2019 (Digital-materials RL11763-SET-0001)
  - Symposium on Mathematics and Post-Classical Theory, 1993 (Box 4)
    Includes invitation to conference
  - Tinbergen Institute, 2000 (Box 4)
    Includes flyer for workshop
  - Undergraduate Education Speech, 1995 (Box 4)
    Includes transcript and related materials for speech given as Acting Dean at Duke
  - University Lectures, 1978 (Box 4)
    Includes flyer advertising lecture at Duke
  - University of Bologna, 1992 (Box 4)
  - University of London, 2005 (Box 4)
    Includes travel documents and correspondence related to serving as external examiner on a doctoral thesis
  - University of Quebec - Montreal, 2004 (Box 4)
    Includes flyer advertising lecture
  - University of Venice, 1991-1993 (Box 4)
    Includes correspondence related to visiting professorship at the university
  - Wellesley Conference, 1986 (Box 4)
    Includes correspondence and other materials related to conference on the rhetoric of economics organized by Arjo Klamer at Wellesley College
- Writings, 1930-2012; undated; 3
  This series documents Weintraub's scholarly writings, including collaborations with Till Duppe, Ted Gayer, Daniel Graham, and Phil Mirowski, among others, and work as an editor of the journal History of Political Economy. Files are arranged alphabetically by title, preserving original arrangement.
  - Articles, Book Chapters, and Other Papers, 1969-2012; undated; 1
    This subseries includes reprints, copies, drafts, and other related materials for Weintraub's scholarly writings in academic journals, edited volumes, and other outlets. Files are arranged alphabetically by title.
    - A Dynamic Model of Firm Entry, 1969-1971 (Box 4)
      Reprint, working paper, and related correspondence
    - A Stochastic Stock-Flow Model, 1969 (Box 4)
      Working paper, draft, and related correspondence
    - Allais, Stability, and Liapunov Theory, 1991 (Box 4)
      Reprint
    - Antisemitism Project, 2003-2012 (Digital-materials RL11763-SET-0002)
    - Appraising General Equilibrium Analysis, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
      Reprint, drafts, and related correspondence
    - Archiving the History of Economics, 1998 (Box 4)
      Reprint, draft, and related correspondence
    - Articles, 1980-2016 (Digital-materials RL11763-SET-0002)
    - Axiomatisches Missverstandnis, 1996-1998 (Box 4)
    - Boland on Neoclassical Maximization, 1982 (Box 4)
      Draft
    - But Doctor Salanti, Bumblebees Really Do Fly, 1991-1993; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Can Neoclassical Economics Be Social Economics? A Comment, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Catastrophe Theory and Intertemporal Equilibria, 1978-1980 (Box 4)
    - Comment on Heilbroner, Economics as Ideology, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
      Drafts and related correspondence
    - Comment on Rosenberg, Lakatosian Consolations for Economists, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - Contextualizing Equilibrium Theory: A Review Essay, 1994 (Box 4)
      Reprint and draft
    - Costless Information: A Limiting Assumption, undated (Box 4)
    - Creating the Neo-Walrasian Synthesis, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Dynamics of the Consumer Price Level, 1971-1972; undated (Box 4)
      Drafts, research materials, and related correspondence for joint paper with S. Weintraub